(月詠)蜘蛛を見た｡
I saw a spider.
あの男の首に
蜘蛛の入れ墨があるのを…｡
A spider tattoo on that man's neck...
A spider, huh?
(銀時)蜘蛛か…
自信はねえが しかたねえ｡
Not much to go by, but oh well.
引っ掛かってみるか 蜘蛛の巣に｡
I'll have to let myself be caught.
In the spiderweb.
(月詠)この件に
ぬしを巻き込んだのはわっちじゃ｡
I'm the one who brought
you into this mess.
Go, quickly!
早く行け｡ わっちもあとから行く｡
わりいな｡
I'll follow behind shortly.
Sorry, but I try not to take a woman's
last minute nonsense seriously.
別れ際に 女が吐く戯言は
真に受けねえことにしてるんだ｡
(月詠)お願いだから 行ってくれ｡
Please go, I beg you.
お前とは
対等な立場でいたいんじゃ｡
I wish to stay as your equal.
お前といると 決心が鈍る｡
When I'm with you, my resolve weakens.
Give up on being a woman, Tsukuyo.
((地雷亜:女を捨てよ 月詠))
(月詠)これ以上
わっちの心をかき乱すな｡
Don't shake up my feelings any further.
とりゃ～！
Pay attention, you idiot!
よそ見してんじゃねえ！
(地雷亜)よそ見は
お前さんのほうさ｡
You're the one
who's not paying attention.
["Once You're Entangled in a Spiderweb,
It's Hard to Get It Off."]
ぎ… 銀時！
Gintoki!
Bastard!
ｷｻﾏ!!
お前は黙っていろ｡
You need to shut up.
月詠！
Tsukuyo!
必ず来ると思っていたぞ 月詠｡
I knew you would come, Tsukuyo.
美しくなったな 見違えるほどに｡
You've become so beautiful.
I almost didn't recognize you.
だが…
その魂は醜くなった 無残なほど｡
However...
Your soul has become
repulsive to behold.
A tragedy.
ｷ… ｷｻﾏ いったい 誰じゃ!?
Who... are you?!
お前さんだろう？
月を欠けさせたのは｡
You must be the one
who ruined the moon.
美しかった ｵﾚの月を汚したのは｡
The one who soiled my beautiful moon.
お前さんだろう？
It must have been you.
なるほど｡
その手負いで その身のこなし…｡
I see...
Your movements are still sharp
despite the injuries.
さすがは 鳳仙を
倒しただけのことはあるな｡
I can see how you were
able to defeat Hosen.
ﾃﾒｴは いったい 何者だ!?
Who the hell are you?!
背中を預けられる存在…｡
Someone you can trust
to watch your back.
護るだけではない
護ってくれる存在を初めて得て➡
Someone who would protect you,
instead of being protected.
捨てたはずの女が
己の内によみがえったか？
Did that bring back the womanhood
you thought to have given up on?
Or could it be...
それとも 惚れたか？ この男に｡
You've fallen for this man?
Gin-san and Tsukuyo are really late.
(晴太)遅いな 銀さんと月詠ねえ｡
もう 帰ってきてもいい頃なのに｡
They should have returned by now.
(日輪)何か変なことに
巻き込まれてなきゃいいけど…｡
I hope that they weren't caught
up in any trouble.
(神楽)大丈夫ｱﾙ！
銀ちゃんも一緒ね｡
Don't worry. She's with Gin-chan.
Though the fact that she's with Gin-san
gives us something else to worry about.
(新八)銀さんが一緒だから
心配なこともあるけどね｡
それより 今日は
すみませんでした 日輪さん｡
Anyway, sorry about today, Hinowa-san.
いろいろ調べたんだけど
たいしたこともわからずに｡
We checked all over but we weren't
able to learn anything.
いいのよ｡ こっちこそ
ﾑﾘ言って ごめんなさい｡
It's fine.
I'm sorry about forcing you to do this.
本当はね
薬うんぬんなんかのことより➡
To be honest, I was more worried about
her than this whole drug deal.
私は あの娘のことが
心配だったのよ｡
Are you talking about Tsukky?
(神楽)ﾂｯｷｰのことｱﾙか？
ﾌﾌﾌ… そう ﾂｯｷｰ｡
Yes, Tsukky.
あの娘のこと
そんなふうに呼んでくれるのは➡
You're the only ones who
would call her that.
あなたたちだけね｡
さえないｱﾙか？
Does it sound dumb?
ううん ｽﾃｷよ｡ 私も
これから ﾂｯｷｰって呼ぶわ｡ ﾌﾌﾌ！
No, it's wonderful.
I'll call her Tsukky from now on.
あの娘 なんでも 自分一人で
背負い込んでしまうﾀﾁだから➡
She always tries to bear
the burden alone.
I'm always so worried.
いつも 心配してるのよ｡
Protecting me and Yoshiwara for so
long, when she's only a woman...
女だてらに ずっと
私と吉原を護り続けてくれた｡
でも あの娘…
自分は何があっても➡
Yet she never tries to rely on other
people when something happens.
何にも よりかかろうとしないの｡
人を護ることばかりで 自分は
誰にも護られようとしない｡
She's so focused on protecting others that
she doesn't allow others to protect her.
今回の件にしても そう｡
It was the same this time.
一人で問題を抱えこんで
考えこんで➡
She was thinking of how to deal
with this problem by herself.
Acting recklessly without considering
the danger to herself...
自分の身を省みないで
無茶ばかりしようとして…｡
I wish she'd be willing to rely on
me when there was trouble.
困ったことがあったら
もっと私に頼ってほしいのに…｡
私が こんなふうに
不甲斐ないばっかりに…｡
It's because I'm so useless like this...
でも あなたたちだけは違うの｡
But it's different with you people.
あなたたちの前では➡
When she's with you, she's able to relax.
あの子も荷を下ろして
立ち止まる｡
対等に 顔をつきあわせ
助けを乞い 助けになる｡
Able to face you on equal footing
and ask for help or offer help.
頭であることを忘れて
ただの一人の女の子になる｡
Able to forget that she's the leader of the
Hyakka and become an ordinary girl.
不思議な人たちね あなたたち｡
You people are a true marvel...
どんなに重たいものを
背負っていても➡
Any heavy burden, any
attempt to shun others
どんなに分厚い壁を
つくっていようと➡
あなたたちを前にすると➡
feels stupid when we're around you.
そうしている自分が
ﾊﾞｶらしくなってくる｡
Hinowa-san...
日輪さん…
それ 褒めてんですか？
Was that a compliment? Or an insult?
けなしてんですか？
It makes me happy to see
Tsukuyo look that way.
私 月詠の
あんな顔を見るのが嬉しくて｡
仕事なんていいの｡
ﾋﾏがあったら たまにでもいい｡
It doesn't have to involve business.
Please come to see her when
you have a little time.
あの娘に会いにきてあげて｡
She needs people like you.
あの娘には
あなたたちみたいな人が必要なの｡
あの人が…
いなくなってしまった今では…｡
Ever since he died...
あの人？ あの人って 誰ですか？
He?
Who do you mean?
昔 いたの｡
あの娘にも 唯一 頼れる人が｡
A long time ago, there was a person
she was able to rely on.
何があっても
あの娘を護ってくれる人が…｡
A person who would protect
her no matter what.
Tsukuyo, I made this clear.
月詠… 言ったはずだ｡
女も捨てることができんﾔﾂに➡
One who can't give up on being a woman
couldn't possibly protect a thing.
何も護ることはできない と｡
その傷の痛み… 忘れたか｡
Have you forgotten the pain
which came with that scar?
Tsukuyo.
((地雷亜:月詠…
護られるのではない｡
If you wish to become one who protects
instead of one who is protected,
護りたいのであれば
女など 捨ててしまえ))
give up on being a woman.
己がかわいさに
己を護る者が➡
How can you protect someone or something
どうして
何かを護ることができる｡
if you're busy ensuring your own safety?
私を滅し
初めて 公に奉ずることができる｡
Devotion can only come
from sacrificing the self.
公とは何か…
幕府でも 将軍でも 主君でもない｡
But devotion to what?
Not the Bakufu, not the
Shogun, not your lord.
己が信じ 己が護るべきものだ｡
It is to what you believe in,
what you must protect.
そう あの人は
月詠を護ってくれていた｡
Yes, he protected Tsukuyo.
月詠も あの人を
よく慕っていた｡
And Tsukuyo respected him in return.
でも あの人が
護ってくれていたのは➡
However, it wasn't Tsukuyo
that he was protecting.
月詠なんかじゃなかったの｡
月詠が ああなってしまったのは
たぶん…｡
Tsukuyo turned out this way because...
誰なんですか？
いったい その人は｡
Who are you talking about?
You may not be the sun which
shines above the people.
太陽のように
人の上に輝けなくとも➡
人知れず
地を照らす月の美しさを➡
But I alone know of your lunar beauty
which secretly illuminates the land.
ｵﾚだけは知っている｡
ｵﾚだけは見ていてやる｡
I alone shall watch over you.
ｵﾚだけは お前を護ってやる｡
I alone will protect you.
That's right...
そう… ｵﾚは護りにきたのさ｡
かつての美しいお前を…｡
I've come to protect your former beauty.
(日輪)江戸随一の腕を
持ちながら➡
He was one of the strongest
Ninja in Edo.
咎により お庭番衆を追われ
吉原に落ちのびた忍｡
Yet he was banished from the
Oniwabanshu for his sins,
and ended up in Yoshiwara.
本当の名は 誰も知らない｡
Nobody knows his real name.
He's known as...
字名は… 地雷亜｡
Jiraia.
The original head of the Hyakka.
初代 百華頭領｡
月詠の…｡
And Tsukuyo's...
Ma-
し… 師匠！
Master?!
Ma-
し… 師匠！
Master...
ｵﾚの化粧も見破れなんだか｡
So you weren't able to see
through my disguise.
皮肉なものだな｡
It's ironic.
己を捨てるため
顔を捨てたというのに➡
I gave up my face when
I gave up my identity,
その捨てた顔が 今や
ｵﾚという存在の唯一の目印｡
yet now that very face serves
as the only proof of my existence.
己の顔となっているのだから｡
The face of my identity...
師匠…｡
Master...
なぜ… ぬしが生きている？
How can you be alive?
なぜ ぬしが…
こんなﾏﾈをしている!?
Why are you doing this?!
知れたこと｡
Isn't it obvious?
お前に会うためさ 月詠｡
To see you, Tsukuyo.
(日輪)幼少の頃から
月詠にその技を叩き込み➡
He was the one who trained
Tsukuyo from a young age
ひとりの修羅を
つくりあげたのは あの人｡
to create a hardened warrior.
月詠に女として生きていく道を
捨てさせたのも あの人｡
He was the one who made Tsukuyo
abandon her life as a woman.
今の月詠をつくりあげたのは
あの人なの｡
He was the one who created
the Tsukuyo we now know.
そして 自らも月詠に教えたように
自分を捨てて死んでしまった｡
And as a final lesson, he sacrificed
himself and died.
死んだ？
Died?
(日輪)４年前 吉原に起きた大火｡
There was a great fire in Yoshiwara
four years ago.
月詠を護るために…｡
He died to protect Tsukuyo.
あの人が護っていたのは
吉原なんかじゃなかった｡
He was never trying to
protect Yoshiwara.
手塩にかけた弟子
月詠だったんだよ｡
He was protecting his beloved
student, Tsukuyo.
感謝してる… あの娘を
命を賭して護ってくれたこと｡
I'm grateful to him for risking
his life to protect her.
ずっと支えになってくれたこと｡
For providing her with support
this whole time...
でも あの娘が誰にも依ることを
しなくなったのは➡
But she remains reluctant
to depend on others
きっと今も あの人の
そんな背中を追いかけてるから｡
because she's walking in his footsteps.
そして たぶん…
あの人が護ろうとしたものも｡
And he probably wasn't even protecting
Tsukuyo as a person.
月詠であって月詠でないもの｡
自分のつくりだした作品｡
He was protecting Tsukuyo
as his creation.
月詠 お前は➡
Tsukuyo, you were a masterpiece that
came from my blood and sweat.
ｵﾚが心血を注いで つくりだした
一個の芸術品だ｡
死を装い 吉原から消えたあとも
ずっと見ていた｡
I have been watching you, ever since I feigned
my death and vanished from Yoshiwara.
お前だけを｡
And you alone...
頼るものをなくし➡
After losing your only source of support,
you were desperate to protect Yoshiwara,
Hinowa on your own.
ひとりで必死に吉原を…
日輪を護る お前の姿を｡
本当に美しかった｡
まるで あの月のように｡
You were beautiful to behold.
Just like the moon.
私を滅し 公に奉じるとき
人は 肉体も善も悪も超越し➡
Humans acting in selfless devotion can
transcend flesh, good, and evil...
その美しい魂だけを
浮かび上がらせる｡
Only your beautiful soul remains.
お前という作品は
ｵﾚなしでは完成しえなかった｡
You would have never been perfected
as a creation without my aid.
だが ｵﾚが存在しても
完成しえなかった｡
But my existence was also
preventing your perfection.
心に拠り所などを持つ弱き者が
己など捨てられるわけもない｡
A weak human who had someone to rely
on could never sacrifice her sense of self.
頼る者などない孤独｡
Once your heart is strong enough to bear
それに耐えうる
強き心を持って➡
the loneliness of having
no one to depend on,
初めて己という存在を
捨てられるのだ｡
you are able to abandon
your sense of self.
お前は あのとき ｵﾚという存在を
失うことで 一度 完成したんだ｡
You were perfected when you lost me.
そう… それで
終わりになるはずだった｡
Yes, that should have been the end.
お前さんたちが現れるまでは｡
Until you all appeared!
(地雷亜)月詠
お前は何もわかっていない｡
Tsukuyo, you understand nothing.
お前に必要なのは 依るべきところ
頼るべき者などではない｡
You do not need anything
to rely on, depend on.
孤独と その剣を向けるべき敵だ｡
You only need solitude and
an enemy for your blade.
見ていろ 月詠｡
Look, Tsukuyo.
You will watch as one who
protects you vanishes.
今 お前の目の前で
お前を護る者は消える｡
そして 夜王に代わる
お前の新たな敵が➡
And a new enemy will be born here
to replace your King of Night.
ここに生まれるんだ｡
この地雷亜がな!!
I, Jiraia!
銀時！ 逃げろ!!
Gintoki! Run!
(地雷亜)ﾌﾌﾌ… 逃げられやしない｡
You won't get away.
You are already caught in my web.
すでに お前さんは ｵﾚの巣の中だ｡
He's floating?!
宙に… うっ！
銀時 糸だ！
Gintoki!
The threads!
ここは ﾔﾂの張った糸が
張り巡らされている！
He's strung up threads all around!
ここでは勝ち目はない！ 逃げろ!!
We can't beat him here!
Run!
《糸!?》
Threads?!
《目に見えねえほどの
細い糸を足場に!?
He's using imperceptible
threads as a foothold?!
最初のｸﾅｲは
ｺｲﾂを張り巡らせるための➡
The first set of kunai was
for setting this up?!
ものだったのか！》
ﾌｯ… 蜘蛛の巣というものはな➡
By the time you notice
that you're caught in a spiderweb,
かかったと気づいたときには
もう遅いのさ｡
it's already too late.
銀時!!
Gintoki!
さあ 仕上げだ｡
Now, to finish you off.
お前の死をもって 月は満ちる｡
With your death, the moon
will become whole again.
あの世で眺めるがいい｡
ｵﾚの美しい月を…｡
Gaze at my beautiful moon
from the afterlife.
ﾌﾝ… まあいい｡
No matter.
あの傷では
万が一にも助かるまい｡
He won't survive those wounds.
Gin...
ぎ… ぎん… 銀時…｡
Gintoki...
(全蔵)知らね｡
ｵﾚ なんにも見てねえ｡
Not my problem.
I didn't see a thing.
ずっと ｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣読んでたから｡
I've been reading JUMP the whole time.
忍者は夜でも ｢ｼﾞｬﾝﾌﾟ｣読めるから｡
Because Ninjas can read
JUMP even in the dark.
ｵﾚは なんにも知らね｡
I have nothing to do with this.
(晴太)銀さん！ 銀さん！
Gin-san!
Hang in there, Gin-
しっかりしてくださいよ 銀…｡
Gin-san!
銀さん！
よかったよ～！
Thank goodness!
このまま
死んじゃうかと思った ｵｲﾗ｡
I thought you were gonna die!
ｱﾎｱﾙか！ 銀ちゃんが
これくらいで死ぬわけないね！
Are you stupid?
It'll take more than this to kill Gin-chan!
But he was unconscious
for three whole days!
(晴太)だって三日三晩も
眠りっぱなしだったんだよ！
それに いくらなんでも
こんな ひどい傷…｡
And these injuries are terrible.
おい… ｵﾚは
なんで助かったんだ？
Hey, why am I alive?
どうやって
こんなとこまで戻ってきたんだ？
How did I make it back here?
[Ugly Girls Club]
(全蔵)ﾌﾟﾊﾊﾊﾊ！ そら飲め飲め！
C'mon! Drink up!
はぁ～ ﾎﾝﾄ 羽振りのいい
おにいさん！
You're a good man.
でも こんなに毎日 遊んでて
お金 大丈夫？
But aren't you going to run out of
money if you come every day?
ああ 大丈夫 大丈夫！
Oh, it's fine.
日輪っつう ねえちゃんから
ｻｰﾋﾞｽ券 たんまりもらってるから｡
I got a bunch of coupons
from the Hinowa lady.
それに ｵﾚ ﾎﾞﾝﾎﾞﾝだし➡
Besides, I'm rich.
こう見えても
昔 将軍に仕えてたんだよ｡
I actually used to work for the Shogun.
また冗談ばっかり！
You're such a kidder.
そんな由緒正しいお方が➡
Why would someone from
a fine background
こんな場末のｸﾗﾌﾞでﾌﾞｻｲｸに
囲まれてるわけないでしょう｡
surround himself with fuglies
in a rundown club.
ん？
I find more beauty in ruined buildings
ｵﾚはね 整ったﾋﾞﾙより
崩れかかった廃墟や➡
and funky caverns than
shiny skyscrapers.
得体の知れない洞窟に
美を感じるんだ｡
ｵﾀｸ すごい廃墟じゃん｡
You're a real wreck.
人っこ一人いないじゃん｡
A rare breed.
どうしたの これ？
巨神兵でも攻めてきたの？
What happened here?
Were you attacked by a Giant Warrior?
なに この２つの洞窟｡
なんで こんな上向いてるの？
What are these two caverns?
Why are they pointing up?
Can I stick it in?
さしていい？
電子ﾚﾝｼﾞのｺﾝｾﾝﾄ さしていい？
Can I stick an electric plug in?
あっ…｡
ぶわっ！
ｲﾃﾃﾃ…｡
Ow...
Bastard!
ﾃﾒｴ 命の恩人に何しやがんだ！
Is this how you treat the man
who saved your life?
海からﾃﾒｴ拾って
ここまで引きずってくるのに➡
Do you have any idea how hard it was to fish you
out of the ocean and drag you down here?!
どれだけ
大変だったと思ってんだ!!
What the hell are you babbling about?
何が命の恩人だ ﾃﾒｴこの野郎！
人が死にかけてるときに
高みの見物決め込んでたﾔﾂに➡
You have no right to talk when you stood
by and watched while I was almost killed.
言われたくねえんだよ！
Why would I come to your rescue?
何でｵﾚが お前のﾋﾟﾝﾁに
助けに入る理由がある｡
それにｵﾚは
ﾍﾞｯﾋﾟﾝの女にゃ興味ねえんだよ｡
Besides, I have no interest in pretty girls.
ﾃﾒｴ あんなところで
何してやがった？
What the hell were you doing there?
月詠は あのあと どうなった？
What happened to Tsukuyo?
Had a little business to take care of.
ちょいと ﾔﾎﾞ用でね｡
The pretty girl was taken.
ﾍﾞｯﾋﾟﾝさんのほうは
連れていかれちまったぜ｡
どこ行った？
さあな｡
Where'd they go?
Beats me. I said that I have
no interest in pretty girls.
ﾍﾞｯﾋﾟﾝには興味ねえって言ってんだ｡
ﾁｯ｡
おい どこへ行く？
Hey, where are you going?
言っておくが
ﾃﾒｴじゃ 野郎には勝てねえぞ｡
Just to be clear,
you don't have a chance against him.
そんな体じゃなくてもな｡
Even if you weren't all beat-up.
ﾍﾞｯﾋﾟﾝさんにゃ 興味ねえが➡
So you have no interest in pretty girls,
ﾌﾞｻｲｸとｵｯｻﾝには興味津々らしいな｡
but you seem to be very interested
in fuglies and old men.
蜘蛛手の地雷亜｡
Jiraia the Spider...
ｵﾚの一世代上だが➡
He belonged to the last generation.
お庭番最強とうたわれた親父に➡
His power was said to rival my old man's,
the strongest of the Oniwabanshu.
匹敵する力を持っていた
と言われている｡
だが そんな腕を持ちながら
ﾔﾂは お庭番を追放された｡
However, despite his abilities, he was
banished from the Oniwabanshu...
その あまりに危険な性質ゆえに｡
Because of his dangerous nature.
悪いことは言わねえ
あの女はあきらめろ｡
I'm trying to be helpful.
Give up on the woman.
ﾔﾂの巣にかかっちゃ
もう救えやしねえよ｡
If you've been caught in his web,
you're beyond saving.
(地雷亜)目が覚めたか｡
どうだ？ 気分は｡
Are you awake?
How do you feel?
Master...
し 師匠…｡
いや 地雷亜｡
No, Jiraia...
ﾌﾌﾌｯ
もはや 師と呼ぶ気も失せたか｡
You no longer wish to call me master?
それでいい｡
お前に必要なのは 孤独と敵｡
That's fine.
You only need solitude and an enemy.
ずっと ぬしの張った巣にとらわれ
もがいていただけだというのか｡
So I'd been struggling in your
web all these years?
信じていた｡ ずっと
その背中を追いかけていた｡
I believed you.
I wanted to follow in your footsteps...
でも
すべては まやかしだったのか｡
But it was all a lie?
お前はいったい どんなｵﾚを
信じていたというのだ？
What was it that you believed in?
お前のことを思い
命を賭して護った優しき師か？
The kind master who gave
his life to protect you?
それとも 身を捨て
公に奉ずる教えを説き➡
Or the harsh master who taught you
the meaning of selfless devotion,
お前から女を奪い
己も身を捨てた厳しき師か？
to give up your identity, to give
up on being a woman?
ならば まやかしなどではない｡
In that case, it wasn't a lie.
ｵﾚは今もこうして
己の身を捨て お前という作品を➡
Even now, am I not sacrificing myself
for the sake of creating you?
つくりあげようと
しているではないか｡
作品？
そんなことのために ｱｲﾂを…｡
Creating me?
You killed him just for that reason?
そうさ｡
お前がかように変わらなければ➡
That's right.
If you hadn't grown weak,
ｵﾚが
吉原に手を出すことはなかった｡
I would have left Yoshiwara alone.
お前が頼る者など
持たなければ あの男も｡
If you hadn't learned to rely on others,
I wouldn't have killed that man either.
ﾔﾂを殺したのはお前だよ 月詠｡
You are the one who killed him, Tsukuyo.
そして これから起こることも
すべては お前が招いた災いだ｡
And the tragedy that will soon play out
will all be your fault.
な 何をするつもりじゃ！
待て 地雷亜！
What do you intend to do?!
Wait! Jiraia!
己を捨てて 吉原を日輪を護る｡
Abandon your sense of self to
protect Yoshiwara and Hinowa.
そうお前は誓ったはず｡ その傷に｡
That was the oath you
swore on that scar...
だが 吉原はお前にとって➡
But Yoshiwara has become more
than a place for you to protect.
ただ 護るだけの存在では
なくなった｡
お前の居場所｡
It has become a place where you belong,
where you can rely on others.
お前の頼るべき者たちが
居る場所へと変わった｡
お前に そんなものはいらない｡
None of that is necessary.
心に張った その巣
根こそぎ焼き払う｡
I shall burn
the cobwebs and roots in your heart.
ま 待て！
Wait!
地雷亜！
Jiraia!!
[Preview]
Screw that.
Screw that to hell.
I'll die before I let that son of a
bitch call himself her master!
["It's the Irresponsible One Who's
Scary When Pissed."]
[Jiraia's spiderweb cloaks all of Yoshiwara.]
[Feelings towards the master, who misses Gintoki...]
[See you next week.]